Guide to the Ampex Collection Addenda ARS.0109
Archive of Recorded Sound
Ampex Collection Addenda
1944-1998
ARS.0109
Archive of Recorded Sound
1 box: 1 folder; 17 open reel tapes (three 5" reels; nine 7" reels; four 10.5" reels; one 12" reel)
Various smaller collections related to the Ampex Corporation, the development of magnetic recording on tape, and stereophonic sound.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Related Collections
Stanford University Special Collections holds the Ampex Corporation Records, M1230. The Archive of Recorded Sound holds the Richard Hess Mullin-Palmer Tape Restoration Project Collection, ARS.0035.
Scope and Contents
This is a group of small collections, assembled from various donors, related to the history of the Ampex Corporation and its role in the development of sound recording on tape and stereophonic sound. Stanford University Special Collections holds the Ampex Corporation Records, and some artifacts described here are part of that collection, despite being housed at the Archive of Recorded Sound. The Ampex Corporation, founded in 1944 by Russian émigré Alexander M. Poniatoff, began as military contractor making components for radar, but became a pioneer in the magnetic tape recording industry through rather unusual circumstances. In 1945, a soldier named John T. "Jack" Mullin was assigned by the U.S. Army Signal Corp to recover examples of Nazi technology from the field. In a radio station near Frankfurt, Mullin confirmed that the Germans had developed a system of sound recording and reproduction using paper and plastic tape. He returned to the United States with fifty reels of audio tape and two AEG Magnetophon brand reel-to-reel machines on which to play them. Following a successful demonstration at an Institute of Radio Engineers conference, Mullin, along with business partner Bill Palmer, approached entertainer Bing Crosby with a proposal for using audio tape in the production of his radio program Philco Radio Time. Crosby thus became the most significant early investor in Ampex's tape recording line. Mullin even worked on the Philco program himself, doing the editing using both the German tape he brought back and with other American brands then in development.
The Ampex Collection Addenda includes two pages of a Philco Radio Time script, possibly with Mullin's notes on the back. The collection also includes an original Magnetophon Tonschreiber tape case with reels and parts. There are also various tapes which came from Jack Mullin via Ampex employee Jim Wheeler, some of which almost certainly came from this case, and miscellaneous tapes from the estate of C.D. (Charles Dewitt) Du Bois, an executive at Ampex beginning in the late 1950s. Finally, there are recordings made in 1998 at a gathering commemorating the fiftieth anniversary of the Ampex 200, the first tape recorder made by the company.
Indexing Terms
Ampex Corporation.; Mullin, John T. (Jack), 1913-1999; Palmer, William A., 1911-1996; Sound--Recording and reproducing
- 1. Ampex 200 Anniversary Party, 1998-04-25; 3 10.5" open reel tapes (Audio 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Ampex 200 Anniversary Party 4/25/98 in Pleasanton, California. Held at the home of Mark Drury. Among those present: Walter Selsted, former chief engineer; John G. "Jay" McKnight, formerly of Ampex, then of Magnetic Reference Laboratories; and Peter Hammar, founder and curator of the former Ampex Museum. Three open reel tapes, dubbed from the original DAT.
  Source
  Donated by David Dintenfass in 1998.
- 2. C.D. Du Bois tapes, 10 open reel tapes: three 5" reels; four 7" reels
  - Professional Recorders in Education, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Demonstration tape, 2-track stereo. Recorded, Produced and Duplicated on Ampex Professional Recorders by Audio Distributors, Inc. (Grand Rapids, Michigan address).
  - Here Is The Ampex Home Music Center And This Is What It Can Do. Ampex Demonstration Tape, Catalog No. AT-20 (2 track stereo, stacked heads, 7.5 ips), 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Groundbreaking - Ampex Audio, Sunnyvale, 1959-01-28; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Date determined from Ampex Collection finding aid.
  - John Halloran Choir. A Christmas Greeting In Stereophonic Sound. "To Mr. and Mrs. Dubois, From [C.AA Frey?], Your Ampex Dealer.", 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    From the printed tape box: "Here for your holiday listening are the voices of the renowned John Halloran Choir singing a group of traditional Christmas carols. These were specially arranged by John Halloran for this tape made for Ampex's friends. This stereophonic recording is sent as a personal Christmas greeting to you and is unavailable in any other form."
  - "To Marketing. Bim Farrar, DeWitt DuBois. From: Gene Russell" (Irish brand tape), 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - "To Dube DuBois, From R. Sprague" (Ampex Corporation sticker with Chicago address, Scotch brand tape, 3 3/4 ips), 1959-04-03; 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Demon Drums. Concertapes Pre-release Copy (In-line heads, 7.5 ips), 1958; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Handwritten identification on circular tape case. Tape was released in 1958 as Duelin' Demon Drums, Featuring Richard Campbell and Harry H. Coon, Concertapes 512(stereo)/411(mono).
- 3. Mullin tapes from Jim Wheeler, 6 open reel tapes: four 7" reels; one 10.5" reel; one 12" reel
  - Bundle 1
    - #7 Hubless Reel: "early '48 Crosby Show from hubless reel", 1948; 1 12" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    - #10 Misc 4, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    - #11 Misc 3: Rainier Herkimer Hamstrung, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Bundle 2
    - #1 Slot 8, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    - #2 Slot 1 "short recording, voice and music", 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    - #4 Slot 3 Tonschrieber Reel 3, Tails Out, 1 10.5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
- 4. Philco Radio Time script (portion), 1947-10; 1 folder (Box 1)
  Two non-consecutive pages of a script for Bing Crosby's Philco Radio Time program, recorded October 3, 1947, and broadcast October 15th. The guest is Dinah Shore. There are handwritten notes (possibly Mullin's) on the reverse sides.
- 5. Ampex Corporation Around the World in Sterophonic Sound. 10th Anniversary of Ampex Recorders. Narration by Ross H. Snyder, 1957; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
- 6. Equipment
  - Ampex Tape Recorder
  - Pierce Wire Recorder
  - Magnetophon Tonschreiber AEG Ton S.b.1 tape case, 1944
    This metal case was brought to the United States by Jack Mullin from Germany in 1945, and has been identified as part of a AEG (Allgemeine-Elektrizitats-Gesellschaft) Magnetophon Tonschreiber. It measures 9.75" x 11.5" x 17" and has "Ton S.b. 1 (Zubehor)" printed on the top. The case held open reel tapes and supplies, and apparently fit next to the actual reel-to-reel player. Inside there are slots for 10" reels. In three slots there are two reels in metal cases and one reel with German writing. No tape is on the reels (see the Mullin tapes for what may be them). There is also a compartment on one side for tools and supplies, including rubber rollers and vacuum tubes (there are two Telefunken LS50s and several smaller tubes in padded holes). A powerful vinegar smell persists, even after seventy years.